This story just keeps getting crazier.
Historia robi się coraz bardziej pokręcona.
So, any new news?
Jakieś nowe wieści?
Yeah. The police said they're holding a press conference at 3 p.m.
Tak, policja zwołuje konferencję prasową o 15.00.
I'll go to Prague Police Station myself.
Sam pojadę na komendę główną w Pradze.
I haven't seen a story like this in my entire career as a reporter.
W całej karierze nie natknąłem się na taką historię.
You've been here all night looking through articles?
Całą noc przeglądał pan artykuły?
Yeah. Thanks.
Tak, dziękuję.
I was able to find what I was looking for.
Znalazłem to, czego szukałem.
Glad to hear it.
Miło słyszeć.
Oh, can you hold on a second?
Przepraszam, chwileczkę.
I'm kind of busy right now.
Jestem dosyć zajęty.
It's about Mr. X in this article.
Chodzi o pana X z tego artykułu.
"Mr. X"?
Pana X?
Yes, he's in this article
Tak, z tego artykułu
from three years ago called "The Truth About Ex-Czechoslovakia Secret Police."
sprzed trzech lat: „Prawda o byłej czechosłowackiej bezpiece”.
Ah, yes.
No tak.
The article about how the German right-wingers, who grew immensely
To artykuł o tym, jak niemiecka skrajna prawica rosła w silę
in power after the wall came down
po upadku muru i stworzyła syndykat zbrodni
I wrote that one.
To mój tekst.
You did? Would it be possible for me to meet Mr. X,
Tak? Byłoby możliwe poznanie pana X,
the former secret police agent that you interviewed for this article?
byłego agenta tajnej policji, z którym pan rozmawiał?
You said you're a special correspondent from Japan, right?
Pan jest specjalnym korespondentem z Japonii?
Why do you want to talk to that Mr. X?
Dlaczego chce pan rozmawiać z panem X?
Well, you see,
Widzi pan…
I'd like to ask him about the kidnappings and imprisonments
Chciałem zapytać o porwania i uwięzienia,
that occurred here during the Cold War Era.
które miały miejsce za czasów zimnej wojny.
Those are dangerous people, you know.
To są groźni ludzie.
I risked my life to get that story then.
Ryzykowałem życiem, aby napisać tamten artykuł.
Heck, they're still dangerous.
Kurcze, wciąż są niebezpieczni.
-They're causing a commotion even now. -Huh?
- Nawet teraz powodują zamieszanie. - Co?
Do you even know about the Detective Suk incident?
Nie słyszał pan o incydencie z detektywem Sukiem?
I can't believe you're a news correspondent.
I pan jest korespondentem?
-No. -I know you said you can't speak Czech,
- Nie słyszałem. - Nie mówi pan po czesku.
but if you're investigating the remnants of the secret police,
Skoro jednak bada pan schedę po tajnej policji,
you should at least keep abreast of this big story.
powinien pan być bardziej na bieżąco.
Here's our paper with the story. You can read German, right?
Nasza gazeta. Czyta pan po niemiecku, tak?
A young detective, Suk, with the Prague Police
Detektyw Suk z praskiej policji
who shot and killed two detectives from headquarter's task force is on the run.
zastrzelił dwóch śledczych ze specjalnej grupy zadaniowej i uciekł.
Then there's Inspector Zeman's murder, which brought to light the connection
Do tego mamy morderstwo inspektora Zemana, które ujawniło powiązania
between the former Czechoslovakia secret police and the Czech Police.
między byłą czechosłowacką bezpieką a obecną policją.
Suk also exposed the connection between the Prague Police Commissioner
Suk ujawnił też, że komisarz policji i dwóch śledczych
and two detectives with the secret police.
mieli związki z tajną policją.
The three were then mysteriously poisoned to death,
Potem tę trójkę tajemniczo otruto,
while Suk went on to be hailed as a hero.
a Suka ogłoszono bohaterem.
But the special task force had its eye on Suk.
Ale specjalna grupa zadaniowa miała Suka na oku.
Then unbelievably,
Na koniec, rzecz niesłychana,
that Detective Suk goes and kills the two detectives watching him.
detektyw Suk zabił dwóch obserwujących go śledczych.
"An elite detective with a promising future…"
„Obiecujący elitarny detektyw…”
"Once hailed as a hero…"
- „Niegdyś ogłoszony bohaterem…” - Co pan tam mruczy pod nosem?
"Three superiors poisoned to death…"
„Trzech przełożonych otrutych…”
"Whiskey bonbons…"
„Cukierki z whiskey…”
"Muscle relaxant…"
„Środki zwiotczające mięśnie…”
Johan!
Johan!
Contact
ROZDZIAŁ 46 PUNKT KONTAKTOWY
Excuse me. Can you tell me if Jan Suk's mother is here?
Przepraszam. Czy jest tu matka Jana Suka?
-Are you with the police? -No.
- Pan z policji? - Nie.
She's in room 409.
Pokój 409.
-Thank you. -You know…
- Dziękuję. - Wie pan…
Talking with her is pretty pointless.
Rozmowa z nią mija się z celem.
You must be Jan Suk's mother.
Zapewne matka Jana Suka?
Jan?
Janie?
Jan… You came.
Janie, przyszedłeś.
Actually, I'm…
Tak właściwie to…
Thank you for coming, Jan.
Dziękuję za przyjście, Janie.
Come closer so I can see your face.
Zbliż się, żebym ci się przyjrzała.
You should lie down.
Proszę się położyć.
Oh, Jan.
Och, Janie.
Have you received any calls or letters from your son?
Pani syn dzwonił albo pisał listy?
Can you believe it?
Uwierzysz?
My neighbor, Caterina, won't give me back my stuffed animal.
Moja sąsiadka, Caterina, nie chce mi oddać pluszaka.
It's the beloved stuffed animal that Auntie Mary gave me.
Mój ukochany pluszak, którego dostałam od cioci Mary.
Your son…
Pani syn…
Your son is innocent.
Pani syn jest niewinny.
Okay, I'll be going.
Dobrze, pójdę już.
Dear…
Kochanie…
You're always playing detective there, aren't you?
Zawsze się tam bawisz w detektywa.
Where was that again?
Czyli gdzie?
You may think it's a secret, but I know all about it.
Wiem, że uważałeś to za sekret, ale matka wie wszystko.
It's that abandoned building on Bruno Street.
Opuszczony budynek przy ulicy Bruno.
So, you knew.
Czyli wiedziałaś.
That's right. I knew.
Właśnie, wiedziałam.
-I'll be going. -Don't get yourself hurt.
- Pójdę już. - Nie zrób sobie krzywdy.
Be back in time for dinner.
Wróć na kolację.
Once upon a time, in a land far away,
Dawno, dawno temu, w odległej krainie
there lived a nameless monster.
żył bezimienny potwór.
The monster was dying to have a name.
Potwór marzył o tym, żeby mieć imię.
Once upon a time, in a land far away,
Dawno, dawno temu, w odległej krainie
there lived a nameless monster.
żył bezimienny potwór.
I got us some food. And a newspaper.
Kupiłem nam jedzenie. I gazetę.
You've become quite the celebrity.
Jesteś dosyć sławny.
I guess nobody's found out about the safe deposit box key, tape,
Zakładam, że nikt nie wie
I wouldn't be so sure.
Nie byłbym tego taki pewien.
But it's better out there than with us.
Lepiej, że są tam niż z nami.
You know, after reading the articles about these murders,
Po przeczytaniu artykułów te morderstwa
they sure resemble the ones that happened before.
bez wątpienia przypominają tamte sprzed lat.
Which ones?
Jakie?
They happened ten years ago in Düsseldorf, Germany.
Miały miejsce dziesięć lat temu w Düsseldorfie, w Niemczech.
The director and two doctors of a certain hospital
Dyrektor i dwóch lekarzy szpitala
were killed with poisoned candy,
zostali otruci cukierkami,
and the suspect was a promising young surgeon.
a podejrzanym był młody, zdolny chirurg.
What happened to him?
Co się z nim stało?
He's still on the run trying to prove his innocence.
Jest zbiegiem, który próbuje udowodnić swoją niewinność.
You're better off than he is. You've got me as a witness.
I tak jesteś w lepszej sytuacji. Masz mnie jako świadka.
That woman you passed on the stairs to my apartment…
Kobieta, która cię minęła na schodach do mieszkania…
Do you mean the blonde beauty?
Pytasz o blond piękność?
If she's the murderer, we've got nothing unless we find her!
Jeśli jest morderczynią, nie mamy nic, dopóki jej nie znajdziemy.
Suk…
Suk…
Am I supposed to keep running until then?
Mam uciekać do tego czasu?
Why the heck has this happened to me?
Dlaczego mnie to spotkało?
-What have I done? -Calm down.
- Co ja takiego zrobiłem? - Uspokój się.
Am I just supposed to disappear off the face of the Earth?
Mam zniknąć z powierzchni ziemi?
Cool it! Just calm down.
Ochłoń! Po prostu wyluzuj.
I told you to trust yourself, right?
Miałeś sobie zaufać, prawda?
Ultimately, the only person you can trust is yourself.
Koniec końców możesz zaufać tylko sobie.
Now, there's a good boy. Come on, let's eat.
Dobry chłopak. No to jedzmy.
This place…
To miejsce…
This is where I played detective when I was a child.
Tu bawiłem się w detektywa jako dziecko.
That was the inspector's desk.
To było biurko inspektora.
I'm surprised it's still here.
Dziwię się, że wciąż tu jest.
I would give out orders from here…
Wydawałem stąd dyspozycje…
like on the TV shows.
jak w telewizji.
Men, this case is a tough one. Give it everything you've got.
Ludzie, to ciężka sprawa. Dajcie z siebie wszystko.
We can't allow evil to run rampant.
Zło nie może się panoszyć.
Fight in the name of justice.
Walczcie w imię sprawiedliwości.
That brings back memories.
Przywołuje to wspomnienia.
Suk!
Suk!
We're surrounded.
Otoczyli nas.
Stay with me, Suk!
Trzymaj się, Suk!
It's dangerous near the window. Get behind the desk.
Jest niebezpiecznie przy oknie. Ukryj się za biurkiem.
-I'm done for! -Pull yourself together!
- Już po mnie! - Ogarnij się!
Who's out there shooting? Czechoslovakia secret police?
Kto tam strzela? Czechosłowacka tajna policja?
Where are they firing from?
Skąd strzelają?
You'll be all right, Suk. It didn't hit anything serious.
Nic ci nie będzie. Nie trafiło w nic ważnego.
I'm going to borrow your gun.
Pożyczę twoją broń.
The tape.
Kaseta.
Suk!
Suk!
Suk, hold on. I'll be right--
Suk, trzymaj się. Zaraz…
They're purposely not shooting to kill.
Nie chcą nas zabić.
The tape!
Kaseta!
The tape isn't here!
Kasety tu nie ma.
They can see me from the window here.
Widzą mnie z tamtego okna.
Mr. Grimmer!
Panie Grimmer!
I'm here! I'm over here, Suk!
Tu jestem! Tu jestem, Suk!
I'll come get you.
Przyjdę po ciebie!
It hurts! It really hurts!
Boli! Naprawdę boli!
Stay calm. It'll be okay.
Spokojnie, będzie dobrze.
Oh, god! I'm done for!
Boże! Już po mnie!
Keep quiet!
Siedź cicho!
Mr. Grimmer!
Panie Grimmer!
Don't talk!
Nie mów nic!
At least…
Przynajmniej…
At least get out and save yourself.
Uciekaj i ratuj siebie.
Don't be stupid!
Nie wygłupiaj się.
They're upstairs.
Są na górze.
They're speaking Czech. What are they saying?
Mówią po czesku. O czym?
The tape!
Kaseta!
It hurts!
Boli!
I don't… want to die…
Nie chcę umierać.
WHO… IS IT?
Kto to?
-Can you speak German? -A little.
- Mówisz po niemiecku? - Trochę.
What are you doing here?
Co tu robisz?
-Who the heck are you? -Answer my question!
- A coś ty za jeden? - Odpowiadaj!
What are you doing?
Co tu robisz?
It's already over.
Już po wszystkim.
They all stormed that building.
Dokonali szturmu na budynek.
They killed that young detective and the tall guy.
Zabili młodego detektywa i tego wysokiego.
Am I too late?
Przybyłem za późno?
It's quiet.
Jest cicho.
YOU… MONSTER.
Ty… potworze.
You're the man from the train.
Człowiek z pociągu.
The Magnificent Steiner…
Niesamowity Steiner…
Mr. Grimmer?
Pan Grimmer?
has done it again.
znów to zrobił.
Mr. Grimmer!
Panie Grimmer!
Hello, Doctor. I see that you finally made it.
Cześć, doktorze. W końcu pan dotarł.
Can you save him?
Może go pan uratować?
He's a good guy.
To dobry człowiek.
Please do what you can to save him.
Niech pan zrobi, co może, aby go uratować.
You've got lots of other patients too.
Ma pan też sporo innych pacjentów.
What the heck happened here?
Co tu w ogóle zaszło?
It was probably me.
To pewnie moja sprawka.
It was the other one…
Tego drugiego…
inside me.
który siedzi we mnie.
You see, I'm from Kinderheim 511.
Widzi pan, jestem z Kinderheim 511.
The Magnificent Steiner!
Niesamowity Steiner!
Hey, kids! Are you ready to watch?
Dzieci! Jesteście gotowe?
What adventure awaits us today?
Jakie przygody nas dziś czekają?
If you ever find yourself in a pinch, just call my name.
Jeśli będziecie przyparci do muru, wystarczy mnie wezwać.
I'll come save you no matter when or where!
Przybędę na ratunek – zawsze i wszędzie!
I'm the invincible Magnificent Steiner!
Niezniszczalny i niesamowity Steiner!
The Magnificent Steiner will never let any evil deed go unpunished!
Niesamowity Steiner zadba, aby każdy zły uczynek został ukarany!
I was glued to the TV when Magnificent Steiner came on.
Kiedy puszczali Niesamowitego Steinera, siedziałem wgapiony w telewizor.
The main character was a wimpy young man.
Główny bohater był mięczakowatym młodzieńcem.
He'd always be driven into a corner at a crucial moment.
W krytycznym momencie był przypierany do muru.
But when he woke up,
Kiedy jednak się budził,
the bad guys would've been knocked out by the Magnificent Steiner.
źli leżeli znokautowani przez Niesamowitego Steinera.
Before I knew it, the Magnificent Steiner would actually show up.
Zanim się zorientowałem, Niesamowity Steiner naprawdę się zjawiał.
When I was in a bind, he'd show up
Kiedy znajdowałem się w trudnym położeniu,
and beat up the bad guys.
przybywał i bił tych złych.
The only thing I remember from childhood is the Magnificent Steiner TV show.
Z dzieciństwa pamiętam tylko serial animowany Niesamowity Steiner.
That's all.
I tyle.
I've lost all my other memories of then.
Nie mam innych wspomnień.
Of Kinderheim 511 and everything else.
Nie tylko dotyczących Kinderheim 511, ale wszystkiego.
I suppose you're not interested. It means nothing to you.
Chyba to pana nie zaciekawi. To nic dla pana nie znaczy.
There. I've done what I can for now.
Proszę. Więcej nie pomogę.
How's Suk? Will he survive?
Jak Suk? Przeżyje?
All the bullets went clean through him.
Wszystkie pociski przeszły na wylot.
But the damage between his brachial artery and axillary artery is bad.
Ale uszkodzenia między tętnicą ramienną a pachową są poważne.
For now, I've applied enough pressure to stop the bleeding.
Dałem na tyle silny ucisk, żeby zatamować krwawienie.
That's all I can do for now.
Więcej teraz nie pomogę.
But he's got to get to a hospital as soon as possible.
Musi możliwie szybko trafić do szpitala.
Mr. Grimmer.
Panie Grimmer.
You said it means nothing to me.
Mówił pan, że to nic dla mnie nie znaczy.
But it does mean something to me.
Ale znaczy.
Especially Kinderheim 511.
Zwłaszcza Kinderheim 511.
Now, call an ambulance.
Teraz proszę wezwać karetkę.
We've loaded up three.
Załadowaliśmy trzech.
We need another ambulance! Call one immediately!
Potrzebna kolejna karetka. Wezwij ją!
-How are their wounds? -They require urgent care, but…
- Jak rany? - Wymagają pilnego opatrzenia, ale…
But what?
Ale co?
They've all been given first aid. And it was skillfully done.
Bardzo sprawnie udzielono im pierwszej pomocy.
Skillful first aid?
Sprawnie udzielona pierwsza pomoc?
It's on the news.
Jest w wiadomościach.
What are they saying?
Co mówią?
It's in Czech, so I don't understand. But I know what hospital they're at.
Mówią po czesku, więc nic nie rozumiem. Wiem tylko, w którym są szpitalu.
Jakub Zima Memorial Hospital.
Szpital Kliniczny im. Jakuba Zimy.
I'm sure the police will arrest Suk for it.
Na pewno aresztują za to Suka.
The thing is…
Rzecz w tym…
He's innocent, isn't he?
Jest niewinny?
Yeah.
Tak.
I should probably go and tell them my story.
Powinienem pójść i powiedzieć moją wersję.
Dr. Tenma, how did you know--
Doktorze Tenma, skąd pan wiedział…
Forget about me. What you said earlier…
Proszę o mnie zapomnieć. To, co pan mówił…
about Kinderheim 511. I want to hear about that.
o Kinderheim 511. Chcę wiedzieć więcej.
To be honest, I don't remember much about it.
Szczerze mówiąc, niewiele pamiętam.
I can't remember it.
Nic nie pamiętam.
Except for a few fragments.
Jakieś urywki.
Dark corridors.
Ciemne korytarze.
Stains on the ceiling.
Plamy na suficie.
The creaking of doors.
Skrzypienie podłóg.
Musty beds.
Zatęchłe łóżka.
My memories only become clearer a little while after I got out of there.
Mam jaśniejsze wspomnienia dopiero po wyjściu stamtąd.
I was told that I was 14 then.
Ponoć miałem wtedy 14 lat.
Now that I look back, I remember being placed in an odd school
Pamiętam, jak mnie zapisali do dziwnej szkoły
and being given a name.
i dali imię.
Wolfgang Grimmer.
Wolfgang Grimmer.
My home was in an extremely artificial town.
Mój dom był w niezwykle sztucznym mieście.
I wasn't allowed out of that area.
Nie wypuszczano mnie z tamtego miejsca.
A man played my father. A woman played my mother.
Mężczyzna odgrywał rolę mojego ojca, kobieta – matki.
I was made to study several different languages.
Kazano mi się uczyć kilku języków.
Russian, English, Spanish, French.
Rosyjskiego, angielskiego, hiszpańskiego, francuskiego.
You were raised to be a spy?
Wychowano pana na szpiega?
What do you think was the most difficult thing to learn?
Jak pan myśli? Czego najtrudniej było się nauczyć?
How to smile.
Jak się uśmiechać.
Well then, I'd better get to the hospital Suk's at.
Dobra, pójdę odwiedzić Suka w szpitalu.
But Mr. Grimmer, I saw in the newspaper
Panie Grimmer, w gazecie pisano,
that you're wanted as a person of interest.
że poszukują pana jako podejrzanego.
I'm the only person who can prove Suk's innocence.
Tylko ja mogę wykazać niewinność Suka.
The Door to Nightmares
ROZDZIAŁ 47 DRZWI DO KOSZMARU